<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A French prophecy, or, An admonition to the English, concerning their near approaching danger and the means to escape it. Being a prediction of a gentleman of quality in Languedoc, concerning the downfall of the French king, and several other things relating to England. / Translated from the French copy.</title>
            <title>Avis pour les fidelles d'Angleterre. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09165</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 124064187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177269</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">124064187</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 124064187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192269</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192269)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2910:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A French prophecy, or, An admonition to the English, concerning their near approaching danger and the means to escape it. Being a prediction of a gentleman of quality in Languedoc, concerning the downfall of the French king, and several other things relating to England. / Translated from the French copy.</title>
                  <title>Avis pour les fidelles d'Angleterre. English.</title>
                  <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656. Prediction concerning a coming persecution of Protestants.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London, with licence,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Contains a translation of: Avis pour les fidelles d'Angleterre.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Toronto Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192269:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A FRENCH PROPHECY:</hi> OR, AN ADMONITION TO THE ENGLISH, CONCERNING <hi>THEIR NEAR APPROACHING DANGER, AND THE MEANS TO ESCAPE IT.</hi> Being a Prediction of a Gentleman of Quality in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc,</hi> concerning the Downfall of the <hi>French King,</hi> and ſeveral other Things relating to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the French Copy, and printed at London, with Licence, Feb.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE following paper accidentally fell into the hands of the Editor, bound up with a number of other fugitive pieces.—The title ſtruck him, as every thing that may ſeem to have any reference to the great events of the preſent time is ready to do. He lays no undue ſtreſs upon extraordinary admonitions, much leſs upon preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to modern prophecy; ſeeing we have Moſes and the Prophets, and the holy Apoſtles, to teſtify unto us; a more ſure word of prophecy to which we do well to take heed. Yet it would be wrong to limit the divine ſovereignty as to the ways in which Providence may give warning to a guilty people, and impreſs the minds of ſome with regard to approaching danger.—The following is written in a pious ſtrain, and bears at leaſt evident marks of ſincerity and good intention in the writers. Every one is left to judge of the marvellous part of it, as he thinks proper: But whatever opinion he may form of that; the advice given may appear both ſalutary and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for Britain in the preſent awful criſis. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſented without farther comment, and without alteration, except in one or two phraſes wherein the Engliſh tranſlation does not ſo exactly expreſs the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the French original.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:192269:2"/>
            <head>Introduction by the Engliſh Publiſher.</head>
            <p>THE original French of the following Admonition I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived lately in Holland of the Author, whoſe name is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſubſcribed; a gentleman of an ancient family in Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc, whoſe ſeat is an ancient caſtle of the ſame name with himſelf, above three Engliſh miles from Montpelier, with a conſiderable revenue thereunto belonging. But he was forced to leave it and all that he had, after two years impriſonment, for religion. And this is his condition at preſent. The Author of the Admonition, which he mentions, was his young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er brother, who died near three years ſince, of about forty-eight years of age, a perſon, as he ſaith, of great piety and credit, and of extraordinary knowledge of things abſent and future. And of him our author received both admonition before-hand of the things here ſaid to have happened to him, and an explication afterward of the myſteries of them, and the ſignification thereof. He is not without witneſſes of the truth of what he relates; but they are diſperſed into ſeveral parts, and ſome of them now in England.</p>
            <p>It was the author's deſire to have it committed to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as ſoon as it might be, and my good-will to my country, and deſire to ſerve them, inclined me to lend my aſſiſtance therein, without much difficulty, both becauſe it doth agree ſo much with the known prediction of Biſhop Uſher, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſtate and courſe of affairs ſeem to agree bur too much with both, in a manifeſt tendency to the accompliſhment of them. And that the Reader may not to be ſo much diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as admoniſhed by it, for his better direction and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on how to uſe it, I thought fit to ſubjoin the principal part of the Biſhop's predictions<note n="*" place="bottom">Biſhop Uſher's prophecy is not here ſubjoined, as it hath been lately and repeatedly printed in Scotland.</note>: which I can aſſure the reader to be no impoſture, but true and genuine, from the teſtimony of two witneſſes beyond all exception. The one, the late Lord Chief Juſtice Hale, who, when I ſhewed it him in writing before ever it was printed, and deſired his judgment of it, told me he had heard him ſay the ſubſtance of it, the ſubſtance of it (repeating thoſe word) twenty times with a great deal of confidence: The other, a perſon whom I ought not to name without licence, but of great honour by degree, and much greater by real worth and virtue, to whom the words were ſpoken hy the Biſhop, and who committed them to writing, and was pleaſed to favour me with the peruſal of the original.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition">
            <head>An Admonition to the Chriſtians of England.</head>
            <p>HE muſt be very blind, who perceives not that the wrath of GOD hath long ſince been kindled againſt all parts
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192269:2"/>
almoſt of Europe; ſo that he ſeems reſolved to deſtroy all fleſh again as it were with a new deluge, ſince it is but too true, that they have abandoned themſelves to all kind of wickedneſs. But the indignation of the Almighty hath begun to manifeſt itſelf more eſpecially againſt thoſe who are called Proteſtants. And by thoſe means ought we to have been induced to repentance, and the reformation of our manners. But heaven and earth are witneſs, that we have not ſo much as known, or well conſidered, what it is to afflict our ſouls and amend our lives. Hence it is that the judgments of God, which we ſo little regarded, though the decree hath again and again brought forth ſo terribly, have been daily more and more increaſing. This we, in France, have been made to ſee by experience, ſince we neglected the admonitions which were given to us.</p>
            <p>It is now twenty years and upwards, ſince I received a letter, which admoniſhed me of our approaching miſeries [in France] and the means to prevent them: which were, to call together the governors of our church, and acquaint them that they ſhould appoint a 3 days faſt in that church, which ſoever ſhould firſt be attached, [by proceſs of our enemies]; and they ſhould ſee the effects thereof. But I neglected that advice, not knowing whence it came. But about ten years after, when I underſtood that, and ſaw the event of much of that which was foretold, I acquainted thoſe gentlemen with it: but they regarded not what I ſaid; which made the conſequence ſo ſad. There are now in England divers miniſters, who were preſent when I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the letter which was ſent me.—The ſame advice which was given to me, was ſent alſo to Madam Turene, and to the Sieur Rouvigny, and to Mr. Gache, miniſter of Charenton, and to the Synod of Languedoc. And when the author who ſent theſe Admonitions, underſtood that nothing was done thereupon, he wrote thus to me:</p>
            <p>"Very unhappy is that ſhip, which being ſhaken in a griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtorm, the mariners will not be rouſed even by a child to pump out the water, which he ſees running in, till he is forced to cry out, <hi>Every one ſhift for himſelf.</hi> Wo to him who loves not our Lord Jeſus, and doth not carry the Divine Crucified One daily in his heart."</p>
            <p>About eight or nine years ſince, a ſudden ſtroke as of thunder ſtruck me down in the day-time (about 8 in the morning) according to three ſeveral warnings thereof gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192269:3"/>
to me three years before. This was followed about ſix weeks after by a thunder in the night: whereof I had alſo been admoniſhed. Whereupon I called up all who were in bed in my houſe, and we went into the chapel, where we were wont to have ſermon<note n="*" place="bottom">The original is, "au lieu ou je faſois precher." The London copy reads, "the room where we uſed to have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers."</note>, and there read the ſcriptures. While that was doing, it thundered under my feet, tho' the place was paved and upon a rock. We all heard the noiſe of thunder (directly) under me, (who was at a diſtance from them, tho' all in the ſame room,) as loud as it uſed to be in the air, and for ſome time. Yet we left not off our reading the ſcriptures. Thoſe were terrible claps, and myſterious preſages and forerunners of the calamities, which are ready to break out upon the kingdoms of France and England. There are in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſeveral perſons who were at my houſe when theſe things happened: They underſtood not the myſtery of them; but I am able to prove what I here declare.</p>
            <p>About five or ſix years ſince, when I was to leave the country where I dwelt, the author of theſe Admonitions, (who lived ſo Chriſtian a life as none could blame, and whom God had favoured with ſuch extraordinary graces, as few, I believe, in ſeveral ages have heard the like,) depoſited with me a ſealed paper; and told me the time when I ſhould open it. In the beginning were theſe words:</p>
            <p>"O King (meaning the French king), a greater King than thee commands (or rules) thee: conſider of the reckoning thou art to make, ſooner than thou thinkeſt."</p>
            <p>And in the end,</p>
            <p>"O England, if thou make thyſelf partaker in the crime, thou ſhalt take part in the puniſhment."</p>
            <p>The ſtorm is violent, full of horror and deſtruction: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prevent it, that your country may be a country of peace, a fortunate iſland, and a garden of Eden: which is the hearty deſire of your moſt obedient ſervant, <hi>Saint Jean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi>] You, who are watchmen of Iſrael, this is the time to watch and pray; this is the time to cry aloud and ſpare not: "Sound the trumpet in Sion; awaken the ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people: Be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, and ſpeak boldly to Jeruſalem, that ſhe repent, that ſo peace may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, and not ſudden deſtruction; for the thunder has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>[Here a few words are wanting, being cut off in binding.]</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:192269:3"/>
            <head>SOME <hi>PASSAGES</hi> EXTRACTED FROM A SCARCE BOOK, WRITTEN BY THE EMINENTLY PIOUS <hi>MR. J. WELCH,</hi> WHEN MINISTER OF JONZAC, DURING HIS EXILE IN FRANCE; RELATING TO THE APPROACHING DESTRUCTION OF THE <hi>ANTICHRISTIAN KINGDOM,</hi> AS FORETOLD IN THE PROPHECIES OF SCRIPTURE. TRANSLATED FROM THE FRENCH COPY, ENTITLED, L'ARMAGEDDON <hi>de la Babylon Apocalyptique: pr. in</hi> 1612.</head>
            <p>—AS the Lord rained fire and brimſtone from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon Sodom and Gomorrah, and overthrew the cities and all the plain, ſo that the ſmoke of them aſcended as the ſmoke of a furnace;—ſo undoubtedly will the Lord ſurpriſe papal Sodom, as in a moment; in one day ſhall her plagues come, death, ſorrow, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with fire: "For ſtrong is the Lord of hoſts that judgeth her."—In an inſtant ſhall ſhe be made deſolate—her great riches ſhall come to nothing, and "the ſmoke of her torment ſhall aſcend up for ever." "The beaſt and the falſe prophet ſhall be taken, and caſt alive into the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone; and all who worſhip the beaſt, &amp;c." Rev. xiv. 9, 10, 11.—The Lord hath ſeen in thee, and in thy prophets, great and horrible enormities, adulteries, whoredoms, lies, and abominations more than
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192269:4"/>
Sodomitical. Have you not wrought wickedneſs with a high hand? Hath not profaneneſs gone forth from you among all nations? You ſtrengthen the people in their ſuperſtitions and idolatries. Hear then, Italian Sodom! Hear, ye princes of Sodom, and ye people of ſpiritual Gommorah! what the Lord hath pronounced againſt you: "He will feed you with wormwood, and make you drink the water of gall:" Thou ſhalt be made a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation;—ſo that every one that goeth by, ſhall be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and hiſs at all thy plagues;—"No man ſhall abide there, neither ſhall a ſon of man dwell in it:"— for who is like me? and who will appoint me the time? and who is that ſhepherd that ſhall ſtand before me? Jer. xlix. 17, &amp;c. Hear then the counſel he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined againſt thee, O Italy! and the thoughts that he thinketh againſt the inhabitants of Rome: The earth ſhall be ſhaken at the noiſe which ſhall bring upon them ruin. He ſhall come up as an eagle; he ſhall fly, and ſtretch his wings over that great city, and the hearts of her mighty men in that day, ſhall be as the heart of a a woman in travail; "Behold a people ſhall come from the north, and a great nation, &amp;c." Jer. l. 41, 42, 43.— Thou ſhalt become like Sodom in thy puniſhment, as thou waſt Sodom in thy ſins; and thy children as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah;—a place for breeding of nettles, and ſalt pits, and of deſolation for ever. This ſhalt thou have for a reward of thy pride: Even as thou haſt uſed reproaching taunts and boaſtings againſt the people of the Lord, ſo the Lord ſhall be terrible againſt thee: He will famiſh all thy gods. Depart then quickly, ye who are his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, tarry not: Save your lives, your ſouls, your bodies, your families, and your poſterity: "Waſh you—make you clean."—Lo, you are admoniſhed of this. Behold the patience and goodneſs of God leading thee to repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Therefore, while it is ſaid, "to-day if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts," make haſte, ariſe, ſave your life; ſtop not in any place of the plain of this ſpiritual Sodom: Aſcend and ſave yourſelves in the mountain of God. — Arrange yourſelves on the ſide of the Lamb; for thoſe who are with him are called, and holy. Linger not; and if there are any others pertaining to you, kinſman, ſon, or daughter, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them far from theſe places; for aſſuredly the Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192269:4"/>
is about to deſtroy them, becauſe the cry of them is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come exceeding great before the Lord. He will ſend his delegates, and his holy ones, to deſtroy them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, do not ſcoff at the warning; for if you do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and obey the voice of the Lord, you ſhall periſh in theſe judgments. And as for you who have departed thence, tarry not in that plain: Suffer not yourſelves to be allured by the pleaſures, the plenty, the opulence, or delights of it: Stretch not out your tents ſo far as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for the men of it are "wicked, and ſinners before the Lord exceedingly."—Their cry is increaſed—their ſin highly aggravated, and the Lord is come down to ſee, whether it be not ſo. Remember the wife of Lot, who is propoſed for an example to all thoſe who put their hand to the plough, and look back; and lay to heart that moſt alarming word of God, enough to make ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds to tremble; "If we ſin wilfully after we have received the knowledge of the truth, &amp;c." Heb. x. 26, 27, 28, 29, 31. and chap. vi. 4, 5.—"How fearful a thing is it to fall into the hands of the living God!"<note n="*" place="bottom">L'Armaged. ch. v. §. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>"In Egypt the firſt-born and the chief of their ſtrength were ſmitten: So in the Romiſh church (which ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is Sodom and <hi>Egypt,</hi> Rev. ii. 8.) many of their firſt-born and chief of their ſtrength have been ſmitten, in many kingdoms, and are dead, yea, the very poſterity and memory of them are rooted out of the earth, as in Germany, France, Flanders, Scotland, England, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other kingdoms. The deliverance of the churches of God was accompliſhed "by a ſtrong hand, and ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out arm, with ſigns and wonders: <hi>Et quand le pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier ne qui eſt aſſis ſur ce throne tenebreux de Pharao oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental ſera frappe, lors la delivrance ſera accomplie:</hi>— And when the firſt-born who is ſeated upon that darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throne of the weſtern Pharoah ſhall be ſmitten, then the deliverance ſhall be completed<note n="†" place="bottom">Ibid. ch. x. §. 3.</note>.</p>
            <p>"As thoſe who departed out of Egypt were for the moſt part rebellious, and fell thro' their unbelief in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs; ſo ſhall it befall thoſe ſtill who, having left this Egypt, rebel againſt the Lord, in order to return thither. Not even the king himſelf, the higher powers ordained of God, to whom all perſons ought to be ſubject, can again bring back the Lord's redeemed, ſeeing he hath ſaid,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192269:5"/>
ye ſhall never again return this way.—For we muſt "render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſar's, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the things that are God's." We muſt obey God God rather than men. "Wo unto them that go down into Egypt for help, and rely upon their great number of horſes, chariots and horſemen; but they look not to the Holy One of Iſrael:" for they are men, and not God. "The Lord ſhall ſtretch forth his hand, and he who helpeth ſhall fall, and he who is holpen ſhall ſtumble, and they all ſhall fall together. And if ye will return, he will bring upon you all the ſickneſſes of that land, and make them cleave to you: he will make your plagues and the plagues of your children wonderful, even great plagues, and of long continuance.—Betake not yourſelves to the ſhadow of Egypt; for that ſhall be your confuſion, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is a people that ſhall not profit you at all; their help ſhall be in vain, and to no purpoſe, but 'your ſtrength is to ſit ſtill;" and to ſtay yourſelves entirely upon the Lord: "for it is a land of trouble and anguiſh, from whence come the old and young lion," to devour, "the viper and the fiery flying ſerpent" to bite and to ſting.— Let every one caſt away his idols of ſilver and of gold; for your fortreſſes ſhall paſs away for fear, and your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and captains ſhall be afraid of the enſign, ſaith the Lord, "whoſe fire is in Zion, and his furnace in Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem." Iſa. xxxi.</p>
            <p>—"Ye paſtors of the Romiſh church, who feed your flocks with the wind of traditions, the commandments, and ordinances of men, even doctrines of devils, howl and cry! and ye magnificent cardinals, archbiſhops and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, roll yourſelves in the duſt! for the days of your ſlaughter, and of your diſperſions are accompliſhed, and ye ſhall fall like a pleaſant veſſel: your peaceable habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are cut down, becauſe of the fierce anger of the Lord. He ſhall kindle a fire in the houſes of yours Gods, and ſhall burn them, and break the ſtatues of your gods in pieces. Doth not the Lord remember the incenſe you have burnt to them in all the cities, and in all the ſtreets of that great city—you, and your fathers, your kings, the chief men among you, and your people? Is not all this come into his heart, ſo as no longer to endure your wicked and abominable deeds? Order ye the buckler and ſhield,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192269:5"/>
and draw near to battle; harneſs the horſes, and get up ye horſemen, and ſtand forth with your helmets, furbiſh the ſpears, and put on the brigandines. Wherefore are they diſmayed, and turned away back?—The ſwift can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not flee away, nor the mighty man eſcape; they ſhall ſtumble and fall towards the north; for out of the north cometh deſtruction. Jer. xlvi. 3, 4, &amp;c. Go up to Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead, and take balm, O daughter of Egypt; in vain ſhalt thou uſe many medicines, for thou ſhalt not be cured. Declare ye this in Italy, and publiſh it in Naples; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it in Milan, and in Rome, and in all the ſtrongeſt cities thereof: all thy plains ſhall be ravaged, and the ſtrong ſhall fall upon the ſtrong, and both ſhall fall down together. O inhabitreſs of Italy! prepare thyſelf for removing. Thy military men, thy cardinals, biſhops, canons, monks, Jeſuits, and all thy troop of locuſts main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by thee, are as fatted calves; they ſhall turn their backs, and fly together, they ſhall not ſtand their ground, becauſe the day of their calamity, the time of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is come upon them: for thine adverſaries ſhall march with power, and come againſt thee; with an ax, as fellers, they ſhall cut down thy foreſt, although the trees thereof cannot be numbered. Pharaoh thy king with his triple crown, is but a ſound; and the noiſe of thy frogs and locuſts ſhall paſs like the hiſſing of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.—All the fowls of the air are called to the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of the great God; they ſhall all be aſſembled to eat the fleſh of thoſe who take part with the beaſt; and then you ſhall know that the Lord is the God and Reedemer of the reformed churches.—Many kings and princes have ſerved, and made their ſubjects perform great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, againſt the Turks, &amp;c. without receiving their wages.—See then, O kings, and princes, and ye who follow him who rides on the white horſe! Behold the land of Italy, behold the great city that hath enriched her merchants with her wealth, and made them princes in the earth, lo, they are given you for the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of your ſervice: ye ſhall gather the booty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſeize upon her ſpoil; this ſhall be your pay, and the wages of your armies, inaſmuch as ye have wrought for me, ſaith the Lord.—Howl ye, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (Meſſieurs) of the Romiſh church, and cry, Alas!
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192269:6"/>
alas! wo worth the day! for the day of the Lord is near —thy foundations ſhall be overthrown—thy primacy, that thou haſt laid as the foundation of thy reign—thy wicked hierarchy, thy diabolical doctrine, ſuperſtitions, and the burden of thy commandments which thou haſt bound upon the ſhoulders of the nations. And not only thou, but thoſe who ſhall ſupport thee, ſhall fall: thy ſtrength ſhall be brought low; and thoſe who ſhall give thee aid, ſhall be broken; for the armies gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the kings that are with the beaſt to make war with him who ſits on the white horſe ſhall be killed. Rev. xix. 19, 20, 21. Thoſe who ſhall afford thee aid, ſhall be broken: It will be your great wiſdom then, O ye kings, and princes of the earth, who have committed whoredom with her, you her merchants in the ſale of ſouls, ye maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſhips, and all ye mariners whoever you be that trade upon the ſea of this beaſtial monarchy, and all you, who love it, and bear affection to it;—ye will do well, I ſay, to ſtand at a diſtance from it, and venture not to approach, when you ſhall ſee her condemnation, and the day of God's vengeance which ſhall come ſuddenly upon her —If you chuſe not to join with the Lamb, and thoſe in heaven and earth, who ſing, Hallelujah—for judging the great whore—at leaſt come not near, keep at a diſtance for fear of her torments, when you ſhall ſee the dunghill deities, her gods created by the blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their breath, her gods of bread, and graven images are but vanity and abomination. O ye Romaniſts, this ſentence is ſure, "The gods that have not made the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the earth ſhall periſh."—Thy wiſdom and knowledge ſhall periſh: He hath turned your counſels into fooliſhneſs; he will break your bars and your arms, and will put his ſword into the hand of his delegates.</p>
            <p>—A lamentation ſhall be taken up over the multitude of thy people, and the daughters of magnificent nations: the kings of the earth ſhall weep, and lament, ſaying, Alas! alas! Babylon the great city; the city ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful!—They ſhall convey thee to the grave with thoſe who deſcend into the pit, ſaying, Go down, daughter of ſpiritual Egypt, and be with the uncircumciſed. The mighty ſhall ſpeak to thee out of the midſt of the grave, and ſay, Alas! the great and powerful city; "Thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192269:6"/>
alſo art become weak as we; thy pomp is brought down to the grave<note n="*" place="bottom">L'Armaged. p. 138, &amp;c.</note>."</p>
            <p>The Apocalyptic Babylon, the Romiſh church, hath oppreſſed the church of Chriſt; ſhe hath brought it into a harder and longer bondage, than the Chaldean.— Like ancient Babel; ſhe hath inſtructed her young cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in the ſcience of her mythology and mateology, her ſcholaſtic babblings, miſſals, &amp;c. having aboliſhed the language of Canaan.—She hath likewiſe ſet up ſtatues of gold, ſilver, wood and ſtone, all the falſe gods they adore, eſpecially that grand idol the <hi>Maſs,</hi> the great Diana of Italy, the goddeſs of papal Rome. She hath commanded all people, nations and languages to fall down before it, and worſhip it. It is ſhe that hath kindled a burning furnace in all her provinces, commanding thoſe who would not fall down to worſhip the idol to be caſt into it. But the Lord hath marvelouſly preſerved his church, as he did the three young men in the furnace, in the midſt of her moſt bloody perſecutions, that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace ſeven times hotter than that of Nebuchadnezzar, in all the kingdoms, where there was any reſiſtance made to her idolatry. The Son of God hath walked with them in the midſt of the flames. They overcame by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of their teſtimony, for they loved not their lives even to the death: Now they are clothed, in white robes; and live and reign with him;—while many have been raiſed up with the ſame ſpirit, to maintain and juſtify their cauſe before their enemies: But the flame of their fiery furnace hath killed thoſe who at the commandment of that beaſt caſt the children of God into it; witneſs, the violent and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death of ſuch as were the executioners of that bloody beaſt and the inſtruments of her butcheries committed on the profeſſors of the truth: Theſe examples are yet freſh in our eyes and ears: But the king of Babylon in the weſt is worſe and more obſtinate than the Chaldean — for the latter, upon ſeeing the wonderful deliverance, approached, and called upon the ſervants of the Lord to come forth, confeſſing the true God, and made an edict that none ſhould ſpeak a word againſt the God of Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192269:7"/>
&amp;c.—and he promoted them in the province of Babylon.</p>
            <p>But do the great deliverances of the ſervants of God aſtoniſh our Roman Babylon? Does ſhe haſtily ariſe— call out—aſſemble her counſellors, governors, &amp;c.?— Does ſhe ſtrive to convince them that their fires, ſwords, treachery, impriſonments, butcheries, are of no avail? Do they confeſs the true and living God? Do their kings and governors dread the cruel orders; or publiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary edicts? Quite the reverſe. They ceaſe not to heap fire to fire, and to inflame the furnace ſtill more. And though they had ſeen the flame devour their mighty and valiant men who had caſt the children of God into it, at their urgent command, yet the dragon, the beaſt, and falſe prophet, having collected all their force and deceits into one, deſiſt not from ſending unclean ſpirits out of their mouth, to gather together the kings of the earth in battle againſt the Lamb, and thoſe who follow him: for which cauſe that great tree of the papacy that has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo ſtrong and high, ſhall not only have its branches hewed down and ſcattered, but the trunk alſo ſhall be cut up and plucked out of the land of the living.— This is the decree of the Almighty that ſhall come upon the king and his kingdom, when the word ſhall yet be in his mouth, "Is not this great Babylon that I have built, &amp;c." —The voice from heaven ſhall cry, O bloody beaſt, O Romiſh Babylon! thy kingdom is departed from thee. When the ſeventh angel ſhall pour out his vial in the air, a great voice from the temple ſhall proclaim, <hi>It is done:</hi> and then the great city ſhall be divided into three parts, &amp;c. A grievous viſion is declared againſt thee; "the treacherous dealer dealeth treacherouſly, the ſpoiler ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: Go up, ye Elamites, beſiege ye Medes; ye kings and princes who have departed from Babylon, go up and beſiege. O Belſhazar, king of Romiſh Babylon, make a great feaſt to thouſands of thy lords and great men; drink, proclaim your ſolemn feſtivals; praiſe your gods of gold, ſilver, braſs, wood, ſtone, and flour: Make good cheer. But mark the decree of the Moſt High! See the fingers of the man's hand gone forth writing on the wall of thy royal palace, a writing that ſhall make thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance change, and thy joints to ſhake; a writing which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192269:7"/>
none of thy aſtrologers or divines can read or interpret. That writing ſhall be the deſtruction of all thy grandees, thy prelates, princes, cardinals, thy red hats and ſervants. Hear the writing that is written; <hi>Mene,</hi> &amp;c. —</p>
            <p>God hath brought thy kingdom to an end; he hath divided it, and given it—to whom? to theſe ten kings, who ſhall hate thee and burn thee with fire: even to all the birds that fly in the midſt of heaven, who ſhall eat thy fleſh, and the fleſh of thy kings, captains, of great and ſmall;—thy patrimony, and the revenues of thy car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, which are like kings—of thy archbiſhops, and alſo of thy biſhops, and of thy abbeys; and the fleſh of all thy monaſteries, colleges, and ſocieties, both of the ſmall and of the great.</p>
            <p>Ariſe then, ye captains and princes, and anoint your ſhields; for thus ſaith the Lord, "Babylon is fallen, is fallen; and all the graven images of her gods are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and caſt to the ground." The watch is ſet; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is added to prophecy to confirm the viſion.— See the chariot of men, with a couple of horſemen, that come againſt thee—thy defence ſhall forſake thee; thy great river Euphrates is dried up;—thy friends ſhall be turned another way; and thy firſt-born Spain, ſhall keep at a diſtance, and not dare to approach thee to help thee: thoſe who love thee, ſhall mourn for thee, but they will not draw near thee to afford thee help. Lo, I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto you, what I have heard from the Lord of hoſts: So we believe, and therefore we ſpeak. It is he who performs the word of his meſſengers—that ſaith to Jeruſalem, and to the temple, thou ſhalt be built again, even in the midſt of thee, O Italy.</p>
            <p>Hear then, ye kings, who are anointed of the Lord; thus he ſpeaks to you; "I hold your right-hand;" he ſhall ſubdue the nations before you—he ſhall looſe the reins of kings who take part with the beaſt. They ſhall open the doors, and the gates of cities ſhall not be ſhut againſt you. He ſhall go before you, make rough places plain, break in pieces the gates of braſs, and will give you the hidden treaſures, riches hoarded there with the utmoſt ſecrecy, that you may know that the Lord is the God of the reformed churches, who hath called you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192269:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by your names, for the love he bears to his choſen who ſerve him. Be of good courage, and let not your hearts fail you. It is he who formed the earth, and created man upon it, who ſtretched out the heavens, and gives law to all their hoſt; it is he who hath raiſed you up in righteouſneſs, and who directs all your deſigns againſt her.<note n="*" place="bottom">L'Argamed. p. 199-207.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. xviii. 1, 2, 4. One angel proclaims, Babylon the great is fallen, &amp;c. and another voice from heaven ſays, "Come out of her, my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues."— The former voice is a prediction of her ruin; the latter, is a command, pointing out the duty of the children of God to withdraw from her; both are heavenly and divine: The firſt, obliges our conſciences to believe; the ſecond, to obey. He who believes not the Lord foretelling and denouncing her ruin, will not obey the Lord, charging men to depart from her. Infidelity is the cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience. You obey not the divine order, Come out of her; becauſe you believe not the divine oracle, Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon is fallen. Believe, and then you will obey that voice from heaven, "Depart from her, my people." Purge your hearts of infidelity, and you would not rebel againſt the voice of the Lord. If the world believed the ruin and fall of Babylon, men would not remain one hour in her communion. What have you to do, O kings and princes, ſmall or great, with that diſgraced and waſted harlot, grown old in her whoredoms. You have neither part, nor lot, with her: retire therefore to your tents, retire to the tabernacles of Zion. What madneſs, what frenzy, to be found expoſed to the avenging hand of God, in the arms of this whore, when become the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of devils, and the haunt of every unclean ſpirit! What infatuation to be found on the ſide of the beaſt, and of the falſe prophet; whoſe ornaments are employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make war againſt him who ſitteth on the white horſe, having on his veſture and thigh the name written, King of kings, and Lord of lords. He ſhall gather the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192269:8"/>
vintage of the earth, for her grapes are ripe, and he ſhall tread the wine-preſs of Divine wrath without the city. "And the beaſt ſhall be taken, &amp;c." chap. xiv. and xix. Wherefore withdraw from her, for this is her end; this her condemnation, and fixed doom: "for ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth her<note n="†" place="bottom">L'Argamed. p. 269, &amp;c.</note>."</p>
            <p>"What fellowſhip hath righteouſneſs with unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs? What communion hath light with darkneſs? What concord hath Chriſt with Belial? Or what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath the temple of God with idols? Therefore come ye out from among them, and be ye ſeparated, ſaith the Lord God." 2 Cor. vi. 17, &amp;c. Be ye ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated—in reſpect of her doctrine, which is a lie, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of iniquity; it is the mouth of the dragon, the doctrine of devils, the efficacy of error; it ſubverts and overthrows completely the foundation of our ſalvation; it is ſpiritual adultery, that diſſolves the conjugal bond of the ſpiritual marriage with Jeſus Chriſt. He therefore that would be in covenant with God, and who would not drink of the wine of his wrath eternally, muſt have no communion with her doctrine, or her religion. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her religious ſervices, and idolatrous aſſemblies; "I would not," ſaid the Apoſtle, "that you ſhould be partakers with devils," for ſuch is the ſervice of idols. 1 Cor. x.</p>
            <p>—Alſo in reſpect of alliances for mutual aid and protection with them; "Why ſhouldſt thou help the ungodly," ſaid the Prophet to Jehoſaphat, "and love them that hate the Lord? therefore is wrath upon thee from before the Lord." 2 Chron. ix. 2. "Wo to them that go down into Egypt for help," &amp;c. Iſa. xxxi.— "Depart ye thence, and touch not any unclean thing:" Take heed to the interdict, for fear leſt you fall under the curſe, and bring the camp of Iſrael under an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and thereby trouble it. Covet not theſe Babyloniſh garments, theſe ceremonies, and ornaments, nor the wedge of gold.—Keep yourſelves from the accurſed thing: for none may take any ſtone from that curſed city for a corner, nor a ſtone for a foundation; otherwiſe the curſe would fall on the takers, and the whole camp of Iſrael, ſo that they could not ſtand, but would turn
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192269:9"/>
their backs before their enemies. "Go forth then, be ye clean that bear the veſſels of the Lord." "Go forth, and be ye as the he-goats before the flock;" for Italian Chaldea in the weſt ſhall be delivered up to pillage, and all thoſe who ſpoil her ſhall be ſatiated, and the arrows of thoſe whom the Lord ſhall raiſe up againſt her ſhall be as thoſe of a mighty man, ſkilfull to deſtroy, for they ſhall not return empty. Ye therefore who have eſcaped, march, halt not, although you be already far off. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Lord, and let Jeruſalem come into your mind. Come forth, and deliver every man his own ſoul from the heat of the Lord's anger: for ſhe ſhall become a heap, &amp;c.—Go forth, in body and ſoul: Have no communion with her either in her doctrines, or idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous aſſemblies, nor in her ceremonies, nor in her eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical hierarchy and epiſcopal government, nor in her religious cuſtoms and modes, nor in her iniquities, nor in any unequal yoke with theſe who belong to her, nor finally, in aid and mutual protection. Go forth yourſelves, and go with all your houſehold; leave not a hoof behind: and go thence, never more to return<note n="*" place="bottom">L'Argamed. p. 274, &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p>"Be not partakers of her ſins:" Obey not thoſe who would command you or conſtrain you to this; or who would entice and counſel you. Should even your father or brother, your wife or huſband, your companion or your maſter, your lord, your prince, or your king, ſhould your miniſter, or even an apoſtle, or angel, command or counſel you to do ſo, hearken not to them. Gal. i. 5.— Away with all authority, human or angelic, in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of religion, in the matter of our faith and religious obedience. Ye princes and kings, ye fathers and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, command not, conſtrain not, entice not nor draw away others to communication with, or participation in your own iniquities, or thoſe of others, eſpecially to a participation of the iniquities of Babylon, for they are great, and ſhall certainly be puniſhed, both in thoſe who commit them, and on thoſe who are or ſhall be partakers of them.</p>
            <bibl>L'Argamed. p. 274, &amp;c.</bibl>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
